无线网络中包含许多的无线终端节点，空间中传输的无线电波则是无线网络的媒介。由于无线电波的特殊性，同一时刻只能有一个无线终端发射无线电信号，其他的终端接收信号。各个无线终端在竞争无线媒介发射无线电信号时，需要遵循一定的媒体访问控制方法MAC。无线网络MAC协议的设计主要有两大类：基于竞争的随机媒体访问和基于调度的媒体访问。

基于竞争的随机访问MAC协议采用按需使用信道的方式，IEEE802.11系列都采用了这种方式。当节点需要发送数据使用无线媒介发射无线电波时，通过竞争方式使用无线信道，如果在发射无线电波时检测到有其他的无线终端在使用无线媒介，产生了碰撞，就按照某种策略退避等待，然后重新发送数据，直到：（一）数据发送成功；或者（二）放弃发送数据。这种方式的主要好处是当网络中的节点数目较少和数据流量较小时，能够提高无线信道的利用率，同时也无需节点时钟同步，算法设计简单。缺点是当网络中源节点较多且网络中的数据流量较大时，多个节点频繁地竞争无线媒介信道，发生碰撞的概率也较大，容易导致节点发包失败的越大。

基于调度的媒体访问控制协议主要是采用时分复用TDMA的方法，按照事先约定的策略周期性地给各个节点分配一定的时槽，用于数据发送或接收。节点在其他空闲非自己时槽时保持接收或者睡眠状态。TDMA机制少了竞争机制的碰撞重传问题。当网络中数据流量较大，无线媒介竞争较为严重的情况下，TDMA机制是一种较好的无线媒介控制机制。缺点是TDMA机制需要无线终端之间的严格时隙同步，时隙分配算法有一定的复杂度。时隙同步一般可通过GPS来解决，或者使用广播帧的方式。TDMA一般主要是研究时隙分配算法。

信道接入协议有很多种分类。同步信道协议协议是指所有节点在时间上是同步的；异步信道接入协议是基于竞争模式的。收方驱动协议是收方通知发方自己已经准备好接收数据；发方驱动是发方通知收方自己又数据需要发送。单信道信道接入协议是所有的信号在同一个信道上传输；双信道信道接入协议有两个共享信道，分别为控制信道和数据信道；多信道信道接入协议是有多个信道，相邻可使用不同信道同时进行通信。固定分配类协议按照网络中最大节点数量做出传输时间安排，为每个用户分配确定的信道；动态分配类协议使用本地参数来分配时隙，根据时隙分配表的产生过程与拓扑结构的依赖关系可分为拓扑非透明算法、拓扑透明算法和拓扑半透明算法。

由于车载网中，车载终端做为无线终端，数目较多，因此研究TDMA方式是很有必要的。在车载环境中，常见的情境有自组织网络，是由多个车载无线终端组成的无中心、多跳得临时自治系统。这种网络无需基础设施，可快速组网。一般情况下每个节点只能感知其一跳范围内的邻居节点的信息，存在明显的节点隐藏和暴露节点问题。

节点隐藏问题：是指在一个节点处于接收者的通信范围内而在发送者的通信范围外。该节点因为监测不到发送节点的无线电信号，导致和发送节点同时向目标接收节点发送报文，这样子在接收节点出会造成冲突。
图节点隐藏
如图所示，节点B处于节点A、C的发送范围内，但节点A、C无法感知到对方的存在。节点A、C中一方准备向B发送数据时，由于无法监测到另一方的存在，所以有可能节点A、C同时向B发送数据，节点B收到的是碰撞的无线电信号。解决隐藏节点问题的方有RTS/CTS。
暴露终端问题：是指终端处于发送者的通信范围内而在接收者的通信范围之外。节点因为检测到发送节点的发送信号而延迟发送，但实际因为它处于接收节点的通信范围之外，所以它的发送实际上不会造成冲突。由于推迟处理，这样子会导致网路容量降低。

图暴露节点问题
如图，A仅能感知到B存在，B能感知到A、C存在，C能感知到B、D存在，D仅能感知C的存在。实际上B向A发送数据和C向D发送数据时，A和D都能收到正确的信号，这并不会有问题。所以B、C在检测到某一个发送信号时推迟处理是不必要的。

车载自主网络，一般的TDMA时隙分为三部分：控制时隙、业务时隙和接入时隙。
控制时隙用来预约传输数据的时隙，业务时隙用来传输业务，接入时隙用来给新增的节点加入网络用的。特别注意的是，接入时隙属于公共时隙，不对应一个具体节点，所以可能会有多个节点竞争这个时隙，在这个时隙中，竞争节点依然采取CSMA机制，检测到碰撞时也要进行随机退避再重新尝试接入。

WTRP提出了使用信令环的方式，使得最大的延迟限定于环的上限时间，当车辆很多时，信令环会很大，导致最终延迟很大，当拓扑变化变化时，重新配置的开销也很大。
MCS/CDMA使用了码分多址的分配策略。每个车载终端都必须有一个平行对应于所有节点的接收匹配过滤器。当拓扑变化时，重新配置的开销也很大。当车载终端数目大于自由码数目怒时，自由码的竞争也会带来延迟。
LCA协议是依据地理位置来分配时隙，需要事先将地理位置映射到时隙中。
TDMA-W和DRAND主要使用了握手握手信号机制来分配时隙，在移动性有限情况下比较有效。
ZMAC使用了了混合解决方案，每个节点都分配了一个专用的时隙，也可以使用CSMA竞争时隙来改善带宽使用。
上述这些方法都普遍面临着拓扑改变时重新配置的开销问题。

图不同时隙安排图
如图所示，车A的前面发生了紧急事件，这个事件需要通过信息传播给后续车辆B、C、D。按照b）的时隙安排，Frame1中，C和B发送的数据不包含紧急事件，A发送后B才收到紧急事件，而C、D不在A的有效传输范围内而无法感知到紧急事件。接着在Frame2中，C发送的数据中仍没有紧急事件，而B发送的数据中有，相当于在Frame2中讲紧急事件传输给C了。最后再Frame3中，C发送了数据才将紧急事件通知给了D。
而在c)中情况很不一样。A发送了数据，告知B；轮到B发送的时隙时，B已经知道了事件，所以可以发送给C；C发送时也知道了事件，所以可以直接告知D发生了紧急事件。整个过程仅在Frame1即可完成。
相对于随机的时隙分配算法，基于位置的时隙算法处理得当的话，会有不同的效果。
一个传输时隙为常数t，包括了必要的守护时间和传输时间。一个帧的时间为T，所以一个节点所分配的传输速率为   r=1/T。在每个传输的头部包含了一个位图bitmap，用来交换时隙信息。
时隙分配有以下的限制
时间限制：在一跳和两跳范围内不允许有重叠发生。如图VeSOMAC时隙分配.jpg所示，除了A和D之外，其他的配对均在一跳或者两跳范围内，这些配对中时序上不会重叠。
关于时隙分配的信息，是通过交换每个包头部的位图向量信息来得到的。

图时隙bitmap图
一个节点可以通知其邻居节点一个关于当前节点一跳范围内时隙占用情况，所以任意一个节点可以感知到其一跳和两跳范围内的时隙占用情况。这个信息可以让当前节点选择一个不重叠于一跳和两跳节点的时隙。

对于一跳的邻居i和j，i选择的时隙应该能被j的bitmap向量所表示。
需要一个迭代的算法来收敛不稳定的情况。更大的位数能加快收敛速度。
当节点没有数据发送时，还是必须发送数据，其中包含bitmap头部和一个空白内容的数据。
时隙上的先后顺序必须与车在行走方向上的先后顺序一致。参见图不同时隙安排图。这个约束条件唯一不好的就是会降低自配置的收敛过程。
可许时间区域是指那些位图中共同标为0的的时间区域。伸缩区域是指在可许时间区域中还进一步满足先后的逻辑顺序的时间区域。
图 许可时间和伸缩区域时间图.jpg
许可时间和伸缩区域时间图.jpg 讲解

对于新加入的车载终端节点，如果能找到伸缩区域，则直接使用即可。
图 迭代的时隙移动聚合.jpg
如果找不到伸缩区域，则先选择一个没有冲突的时隙，跟在其他时隙之后。
图 迭代的时隙移动聚合.jpg  解释
总得来说，这个协议的核心是，每个车载终端节点迭代的移动自己的时隙跟在它上一辆车之后的时隙，知道所有的节点时隙都满足以上约束。

如果去除先后顺序约束，那么省掉了收敛过程。

一个车载终端节点必须看到它一跳范围的终端节点中bitmap里边自己的那位为1。因此bitmap位图可用于检测冲突。
一个很极端的情况，当所有的终端节点加入网络时，所有节点都选择同一个时隙，都不监听。因此，需要有一个随机的退避。


LOCATION-ASSISTED RANDOM ACCESS SCHEME

图LOCATION-ASSISTED RANDOM ACCESS SCHEME
假设带宽被分为M部分，每个信道只能被一个车载终端占用。多个用户占用同一信道则视为冲突，没有一个用户能成功发送数据。
所有车载终端可通过GPS来获得地理位置。
由于车辆地理信息的唯一性，终端节点可依据地理位置来获取信道。一个位置-信道的映射算法用来帮助终端节点选择信道。

如位置图所示，给位置标位置，分为两维，一维是车的行走方向，另一方向是第二维。最大值K则由道路匝数决定。
普遍来所：
1）终端节点想发送数据，所以广播数据
2）其他节点收到广播的数据时，会回应它们的地理位置信息。
3）本终端节点根据收到的地理位置信息来编号，然后再把编号信息发送出去。
一般来说，信道数目M是小于K*N的，所以多个终端可能会访问同一信道，导致冲突发生。
LOCATION-ASSISTED RANDOM ACCESS SCHEME使用了地理位置信息来帮助用户有效的访问信道。
在这个方案中，一个终端节点会以不同的概率来访问划分的信道。有以下规则：
1) An exclusive function is employed to make the vehicular
location information 𝐿(𝑖, 𝑗) map to a random variable 𝑌
which is about the sequence number of the orthogonal
channel. The function can be expressed by:
𝑌 𝑘(𝑒) = 𝑓𝑘[𝐿(𝑖, 𝑗)]; 𝑘 = 1, 2, . . .,𝐾 ∗ 𝑁
where, 𝑌𝑘 denotes the random variable mapped by the 𝑘-
th location, 𝑓𝑘 denotes the function of the 𝑛-th location,
𝐿(𝑖, 𝑗) denotes the location of a vehicle, 𝐾 denotes
the number of the lanes, 𝑁 denotes the number of the
locations in the studied area.
2) Each random variable 𝑌 has a particular probability
distribution which is expressed as follows
𝑃{𝑌 𝑘 = 𝑚} = 𝑝𝑘
𝑚, 𝑚= 1, 2, . . . , 𝑀
𝑀
Σ
𝑚=1
𝑝𝑘
𝑚 = 1;
where, 𝑀 represents the number of the orthogonal channels,
𝑝𝑚 represents the probability that a vehicle access
the 𝑚-th channel.
3) To satisfy the requirement of the distributed channel
access, the mapping between the location information
and the probability distribution should have the following
properties:
a) For any area, the mapping is identical. In other
words, when the area is formed, the location has
been divided. As well, the mapping of any location
has been determined too;
b) The mapping only depends on the probability distribution
and the relative location of vehicle. But has
nothing to do with the absolute location which is
obtained by the GPS receiver;
c) The mapping only exists in two neighboring geographic
areas which have no interference with each
other.
4) If vehicles in different locations access to the same
channel at the same time (i.e. the values of two random
variables are equal), the collision emerges. Under this
situation, none of the vehicles could successfully use the
channel to transmit. The expression of this situation can


be expressed by:
𝑦𝑖 = 𝑦𝑗 ; 𝑖 ∕= 𝑗
where, 𝑦𝑖 and 𝑦𝑗 are the value of the random variable 𝑌 𝑖
and 𝑌 𝑗 respectively.

冲突可能性和流量分析
In this section, the model of the average collision probability
is derived. Without loss of generality,we assume that the
scenario of VANET taken into account is an area on the oneway
traffic road. The length of the area 𝐿 depends on the
effective distance which can guarantee vehicles in this area
to communicate with each other normally. We assume that
every location in the area has a unique index number such
as 1, 2, . . .,𝑁. Meanwhile, the probability which any vehicles
exist in each location is equivalent and denoted by 𝑝𝑒. The
probability which the vehicle in the 𝑁-th location accesses
the 𝑀-th time slot is denoted by 𝑝𝑛𝑚. Such as the probability
of the vehicle in the fourth location accessing the first channel
is denoted by 𝑝41 as shown in Fig. 3.
Based on the above assumption, 𝑁 ∗ 𝑀 unknown parameters
can be obtained, such as 𝑝𝑖𝑗(𝑖 = 1, 2, . . .,𝑁; 𝑗 =
1, 2, . . .,𝑀). In this paper, we employ the genetic algorithm
(GA) to optimize the 𝑁 ∗ 𝑀 unknown parameters. The objective
of the optimization is to decrease the average collision
probability (ACP) among the vehicles in the studied area. The
optimal values of the probability will be regarded as the basis
for the vehicles to access the channel. In other words, when
the vehicle wants to choose a channel to transmit information,
it will occupy the corresponding channel according to the
probability 𝑝𝑖𝑗 .We consider the general random access scheme
for comparison. In order to compare these two schemes,
some index should be used to evaluate the performance of
them. We can calculate the average collision probability and
the throughput of them respectively. The detailed calculation
process of the average collision probability and the throughput
using these two schemes is shown as follows:
1) Average Collision Probability in Location-Assisted Random
Access Scheme: As mentioned above, a vehicle appears
in any location with equal probability. In location-assisted
random access scheme, the vehicle in every location accesses
channels with different probabilities. The vehicle will suffer
from the collision caused by the vehicles in other locations,
when it accesses the channel. First, we calculate the collision
probability of the vehicle appears in every location accessing
the channel. Then add up all the collision probabilities to get
the total collision probability. Finally, let the total collision
probability be divided by the location number 𝑁, the average
collision probability will be obtained. To obtain the expression
of average collision probability, we first compute the collision
probability of a vehicle in a certain location. In this location,
a vehicle may randomly access the orthogonal channels. If
the vehicle access the channel that is also accessed by other
vehicles, the collision takes place. The collision probability
model of the vehicle in a certain location can be founded as:
𝑃𝑐1 = 1− 𝑃𝑛𝑐1, (1)
𝑃𝑛𝑐1 =
𝑀
Σ 𝑖=
1
𝑝1𝑖
𝑁
Π
𝑗=2
(1 − 𝑝𝑒𝑝𝑗𝑖); (2)
where, 𝑃𝑐1 denotes the collision probability of the vehicle
in a certain location accessing channels, 𝑃𝑛𝑐1 denotes the
non-collision probability of the vehicle in the first location
accessing channels, 𝑁 denotes the location number in the
studied area, 𝑀 denotes the channel number of the wireless
bandwidth divided, 𝑝𝑒 denotes the probability of a vehicle
appears in a location.
Based on the above derivation, the expression of total
collision probability of the vehicle in all locations can be given
by:
𝑃𝑡𝑐 = 1− 𝑃𝑡𝑛𝑐, (3)
𝑃𝑡𝑛𝑐 =
𝑁
Σ
𝑘=1
𝑃𝑛𝑐𝑘 =
𝑁
Σ
𝑘=1
𝑀
Σ 𝑖=
1
𝑝𝑘𝑖Π
𝑗=1
𝑗∕=𝑖
(1 − 𝑝𝑒𝑝𝑗𝑖), (4)
𝑃𝑎𝑣𝑒𝑟−𝑐 =
1
𝑁
𝑃𝑡𝑐 =
1
𝑁
(1 − 𝑃𝑡𝑛𝑐); (5)
where, 𝑃𝑡𝑐 represents the total collision probability of the
vehicle in the studied area accessing the channel, 𝑃𝑡𝑛𝑐 represents
the total non-collision probability of the vehicle in
the studied area accessing the channel, 𝑃𝑎𝑣𝑒𝑟−𝑐 represents the
average collision probability of the vehicle in the studied area
accessing the channel.
2) Average Collision Probability in General Random Access
Scheme: General random access scheme is a simple
scheme used by the vehicle to access channel. In the general
random access scheme, all the vehicles access the channel
with an equal probability that is 1/𝑀. The average collision
probability of the vehicle accessing channel by this scheme
is equal to the collision probability, in which the vehicle in
any locations accesses any channel. Consequently, the average
collision probability model is given by:
𝑃𝑎𝑣𝑒𝑟−𝑐 = 1− [(1 − 𝑝𝑒) + 𝑝𝑒(1 −
1
𝑀
)]𝑁−1
= 1− (1 − 𝑝𝑒
1
𝑀
)𝑁−1; (6)
B. Analysis of Average Throughput
To compare the performance of the general scheme and
the proposed scheme, we derive the throughput in these two
schemes. Some assumptions are made. First, the channel condition
is stable and uniform. Second, the throughput estimated
by the average rate of message delivery over the channel
which is accessed by the vehicle successfully. Based on these
assumptions, the average throughput is obtained by:
𝑇𝑎𝑣𝑒𝑟 =
𝐶
𝑀
(1 − 𝑃𝑎𝑣𝑒𝑟−𝑐); (7)
where, 𝑇𝑎𝑣𝑒𝑟 denotes the average throughput of the orthogonal
channel, 𝐶 denotes the total channel capacity of the
bandwidth, 𝑀 denotes the number of the orthogonal channel,
𝑃𝑎𝑣𝑒𝑟−𝑐 denotes the collision probability when a vehicle
access the channel.
IV. PROBLEM FORMULATION AND SOLUTION
According to (4) and (5), we can see the average collision
probability is dependent on the L2C mapping. We should
optimize the parameters of the L2C mapping in order to get a
minimum average collision probability. The objective function
and the constraint conditions of the optimization problem can
be written as
(1) Objective function
𝑃𝑡𝑐 = 1− 𝑃𝑡𝑛𝑐 = 1−
𝑁
Σ
𝑘=1
𝑀
Σ 𝑖=
1
𝑝𝑘𝑖
𝑁
Π
𝑗=1
𝑗∕=𝑖
(1 − 𝑝𝑒𝑝𝑗𝑖); (8)
(2) Constraint conditions
𝑠.𝑡.⎧⎨⎩
𝑀 Σ
𝑗=
1
𝑝𝑖𝑗 = 1 𝑖 = 1, 2, . . .,𝑁
0 ≤ 𝑝𝑖𝑗 ≤ 1 𝑗 = 1, 2, . . . , 𝑀.
(𝑀 <𝑁) (9)
The expression of the total collision probability in the
location-assisted random access scheme has multivariable,
high-ordered, non-linear characteristic. This challenge makes
the optimization process become difficult. Meanwhile, common
method to solve the optimization problem can not accomplish
the optimality of this model. Genetic Algorithm (GA)
optimizer is an adaptive heuristic search algorithm premised
on the evolutionary theories of natural selection and genetic
which is an intelligent exploitation of a random search within
a defined search space to solve the optimization problem, and
can search for approximate global optimal solution.
The basic concept of GA is based on the principle of
survival of the fittest by Charles Darwin. According to this
principle, GA must perform the following five steps: 1) encode
all the parameters in the objective function and construct the
individual chromosome; 2) establish and initialize the initial
population; 3) assign fitness values to individuals according
to the objective function value; 4) duplicate the individuals
of high fitness values from the population; 5) achieve the
operation of crossover, mutation and recombination among
the population to produce individuals of the next generation.
Through the reiteration of above genetic operation, a group of
individuals will be acquired to make the function of the total
collision probability get the minimum value. By the decoding
operation, the real values of all the parameters in the function
of the total collision probability can be obtained. These real
values make the objective function reach the approximate
global optimal solution.
V. SIMULATION RESULTS
In this section, we present the performance comparison
between the two channel access schemes. In the simulation,
the Poisson Point Process is used to describe the location
distribution of vehicles. The frequency of the change in vehicle
topology is much less than the rate of the communications.
Therefore, we can observe the distribution in a snapshot and
assume that in the snapshot the vehicles evenly distributed
in the area randomly. Each vehicle has a unique information
of location at any time (i.e., no overlap of location) and the
probability that a vehicle appears in a location (i.e., 𝑝𝑒) is
a constant. Meanwhile, we assume that the connectivity is
determined by the distances among vehicles.
To improve the utilization of the wireless channel, the
number of orthogonal channels 𝑀 should be as small as
possible. But the smaller the value of 𝑀, the larger the average
collision probability. The number of the channels 𝑀 reaches
the optimal when it makes the throughput reach maximal. Due
to the fact that the vehicles should keep a safety distance
between each other when they travel on the road, we set the
length of every location as 10 meters. Moreover, in order
to ensure that vehicles can communicate with each other
effectively, we set the length of the area as 500 meters a
typical communication range in IEEE 802.11p. By referring
to the DSRC technique, we set the channel capacity 𝐶 as
20Mbps. Then the location number 𝑁 is 50. The change of 𝑝𝑒
has profound effect on the average probability. We choose two
values of 𝑝𝑒. The little value of 𝑝𝑒 presents that a small number
of vehicles appears on the road. The large value of 𝑝𝑒 presents
that the road is adequately crowd. In the simulation, we set
the small and the large value as 0.3 and 0.7, respectively.
In the process of the GA optimization, Gray code coding
method is used to achieve the parametric coding and 20
binary bits represent a parameter. In addition, we select the
function of the total collision probability as the fitness function
and assign fitness values based on the ranking method. The
probability of the crossover and the mutation set as 0.7 and
0.035.
First, we fix the probability of the vehicle appearing in
a location by 𝑝𝑒 = 0.3. We observe the variation of the
average throughput of the channel and the average collision
probability of channel access with the variation of the number
of orthogonal channels. From the Fig. 4, we can see that,
in the general access scheme, when 𝑀 = 15,
the average
throughput achieves the maximum. The average throughput
in the proposed scheme outperforms out of that in the general
scheme by as much as 16%. In the other hand, from Fig. 5 we
can see that the average probability in our scheme is always
lower than the general scheme. Especially, in the maximum
of the throughput (i.e., 𝑀 = 17), the 𝑃𝑎𝑣𝑒−𝑐 decreases by
13.7%. Meanwhile, the throughput in our scheme increases
by 19% than the general scheme.
Second, we fix the probability of the vehicle appearing
in a location (i.e., 𝑝𝑒 = 0.7) and observe the variation
of the average throughput of the channel and the average
collision probability of channel access with the variation of
the number of orthogonal channels. From the Fig. 6 we can
see that, in the general access scheme, the maximum of
the average throughput appears in 𝑀 = 35.
At this point,
in the location-assisted random access scheme, the average
throughput increases by 83% than in the general random
access scheme. Meanwhile, form the Fig. 6 we also can see
that when 𝑀 = 25, the performance of the average throughput
has already reached an remarkable performance. In addition,
form the Fig. 7 we can see that 𝑃𝑎𝑣𝑒−𝑐 in our scheme is
lower than in the general scheme. Furthermore along with the
increase of 𝑀, the decreasing degree of the average collision
probability increases observably.
VI. CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK
In this paper, a location-assisted random access scheme
is proposed for VANETs. In the scheme, each vehicle node
access to the channel according to a L2C mapping table.
The average collision probability of channel access is reduced
significantly. The average throughput is obviously improved.
Simulation results show that the average throughput in our
scheme outperforms that in the general random access scheme,
when the number of the orthogonal channels is given, especially
in the situation of traffic congestion. In our future work,
a more practical model for the random distribution of vehicles
will be considered. In addition, fading and shadowing effects
may be taken into account in the radio propagation model.

遗传算法也是计算机科学人工智能领域中用于解决最优化的一种搜索启发式算法，是进化算法的一种。这种启发式通常用来生成有用的解决方案来优化和搜索问题。进化算法最初是借鉴了进化生物学中的一些现象而发展起来的，这些现象包括遗传、突变、自然选择以及杂交等。遗传算法在适应度函数选择不当的情况下有可能收敛于局部最优[1]，而不能达到全局最优。
遗传算法的基本运算过程如下：
a)初始化：设置进化代数计数器t=0，设置最大进化代数T，随机生成M个个体作为初始群体P(0)。
b)个体评价：计算群体P(t)中各个个体的适应度。
c)选择运算:将选择算子作用于群体。选择的目的是把优化的个体直接遗传到下一代或通过配对交叉产生新的个体再遗传到下一代。选择操作是建立在群体中个体的适应度评估基础上的。
d)交叉运算：将交叉算子作用于群体。遗传算法中起核心作用的就是交叉算子。
e)变异运算：将变异算子作用于群体。即是对群体中的个体串的某些基因座上的基因值作变动。
群体P(t)经过选择、交叉、变异运算之后得到下一代群体P(t+1)。
f)终止条件判断:若t=T,则以进化过程中所得到的具有最大适应度个体作为最优解输出，终止计算。
