车载环境下的媒体接入控制
Media Access Control in Vehicular Environment

摘要
随着互联网和交通系统的不断发展，二者互相融合的车联网（The Internet of Vehicles）受到越来越多研究机构和厂商的关注和研究。车联网是当今研究前沿物联网的一个集合，是物联网应用于智能交通系统（Intelligent Transport System）领域的具体形式。
车联网是汽车高速移动的环境下，通过车辆上的无线收发装置，以及路边固定的无线收发装置，通过通信协议组合构建连接起来的一个车用互联网。车联网涉及到无线技术、通信技术、数据处理技术等各种技术，涉及面广。车联网旨在提供一个车-车、车-路高速的数据通信方式，实时准确整合车载信息，解决交通拥堵问题，确保行车安全，同时提供其他的商务娱乐应用，最终实现智能城市管理。
汽车做为车载环境下的移动媒体，需要遵循特定的接入控制规则以接入车载网。现有成熟的媒体接入控制主要是国际电子电气工程师协会IEEE802.11无线技术，采用CSMA/CA（Carrier Sense Multiple Access with Collision Avoidance）的媒体访问控制技术MAC（Media Access Control，介质访问控制）机制，CSMA/CA中当节点发送数据遇到载波链路冲突时，要退避一个随机时间。除了CSMA/CA控制机制外，还有TDMA（Time Division Multiple Access，时分多址）机制，通过分配时间片的方式调度整个系统的通信。
本论文在调查研究无线网络媒体接入控制技术和车联网相关技术的基础上，研究CSMA和TDMA这两种不同的接入控制，并在Linux操作系统编程和Linux内核网络子系统的基础上，借助Linux开放的网络协议栈接口，实现一个简单的媒体控制接入系统平台，涉及到双网卡通信方式和802.11p协议方式。

关键词： 车载网 媒体接入控制 CSMA/ TDMA Linux网络编程
 


Abstract
With the progressive development of the Internet and the transport system , research institutes and manufacturers have aroused more and more concern and study  about the merging The Internet of Vehicles. The Internet of Vehicles is a subset of today's the leading edge of scientific research , also is the concrete format used in Intelligent Transport System of The Internet of Things .
The Internet of Vehicles is a vehicle – use network at high speed vehicle environment, which is formed by the high speed moving vehicle with the wireless transceiver , and a stationary roadside with the wireless transceiver, constructed by communications protocol.
The Internet of Vehicles comes to a wildly and variety of technologies such as wireless networking technology, communications technology , data processing technology. The Internet of Vehicles is intended to provide a high speed data communication between vehicle - vehicle, vehicle - roadside, integrate the vehicle information real-timely and accurately , solve the traffic congestion problems ,  ensure road safety , also provide additional business and entertainment applications , and ultimately management the city smartly.
The automotive vehicle must follow a specific vehicle access control rule as a movable media to  access the  network . Currently the mature media access control is mainly the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)802.11 wireless Media Access Control technologies using CSMA / CA (Carrier Sense Multiple Access with Collision Avoidance) , when a wireless node transmits data carrier links conflict happen, it should backoff a random time . In addition to the CSMA / CA control mechanism , TDMA (Time Division Multiple Access) is another choice, which communicate via the scheduler allocated time slices .
This thesis research about wireless network media access control technology and vehicle networking technology on the basis of the relevant research CSMA and TDMA different media access control. With the Linux operating system programming , the Linux kernel networking subsystem ,and the Linux open network protocol stack interface, achieve a simple media access control system platform, include dual-NIC communication and 802.11p protocol.